Guide to the Richard C. Hottelet papers, 1947-2004 MS2228
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Richard C. Hottelet papers
1947-2004
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Hottelet, Richard C.
MS2228
15.5 Linear Feet
This collection contains transcripts of radio and television broadcasts, personal notes, correspondence, reporters notebooks, and clippings pertaining to the work of Richard C. Hottelet from 1947-2004.
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donated in 2007 by Richard Hottelet. Second accession (2019.072) sent from his estate in 2019.
Arrangement
This collection is minimally processed and series have not been devised. The material arrived in no particular order. It is currently arranged loosely by type of document with a chronologic or alphabetic arrangement within those broad groupings.
Historical or Biographical Note
Richard Curt Hottelet, born September 22, 1917, was a foreign correspondent for the United Press in Berlin (1938-41). At the start of World War II he was arrested by the German secret police under suspicion of being a spy. After spending 5 months incarcerated, Hottelet was released during a U.S.-German prisoner exchange.
Hottelet was hired by Edward R. Murrow in 1944. On D-Day he aired the first eyewitness account of the seaborne invasion of Normandy; Hottelet rode along in a bomber that attacked Utah Beach six minutes before H-Hour. He also covered the Battle of the Bulge for CBS. Later he parachuted to safety when the plane he was in was shot down by enemy fire.
His credentials include: US Office of War Information, Washington, London, N Africa, Italy 1941-43; War Correspondent for CBS News, European Theater, 1944-45; Berlin 1947; Washington and New York 1947-50; Berlin, Bonn, Central Europe 1950-57; Washington, New York Radio & TV anchor. United Nations Correspondent, many foreign assignments: Vietnam, Middle East, Africa, Latin America, Europe, SE Asia, Soviet Union, India, Pakistan 1960-1985; Moderator America and the World Radio for Council on Foreign Relations 1989-1995.
After leaving CBS Hottelet continued to write op-ed pieces and lecture. As of 2001 he began writing commentary for the Christian Science Monitor, which he continued to do through 2005. Hottlet guest lectured classes in the early 2000s at George Washington University and participated in the opening of the University's Media and Public Affairs Building in 2002. He also appeared as a panelist on GW's Kalb Report forum series at The National Press Club.
Hottelet was the last living journalist from the original World War II-era group of Murrow's Boys, journalists tutored and/or encouraged by Edward R. Murrow at CBS. Ricahrd Hottelet died December 17, 2014 at his home in Wilton, Connecticut.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains transcripts of radio and television broadcasts, reporters notebooks, personal notes, correspondence, and clippings pertaining to the work of journalist Richard C. Hottelet from 1947-2004.
Separated Materials
The book Synchronoptische Weltgeschichte by Peters was added to the Special Collections book collection. The catalog record has a note to indicate it is a gift of Richard C. Hottelet.
Journalism; Politics and government; World War, 1939-1945; Radio broadcasting -- United States; Washington (D.C.); Europe; Hottelet, Richard C.
- Transcripts and notes, 03/28/1948-12/29/1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Transcripts and notes, 03/07/1949-06/30/1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Transcripts and notes, 07/01/1949-12/30/1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Transcripts and notes, 01/02/1950-03/31/1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Transcripts and notes, 05/13/1950-10/19/1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Transcripts and notes, 10/21/1950-05/16/1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Transcripts and notes, 05/18/1952-09/03/1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Transcripts and notes, 09/04/1954-12/27/1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Transcripts and notes, 01/02/1955-05/31/1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Transcripts and notes, 06/03/1955-10/02/1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Transcripts and notes, 09/1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Transcripts and notes, 10/04/1955-12/25/1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Transcripts and notes, 01/01/1956-06/21/1956 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Transcripts and notes, 08/06/1956-12/16/1956 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Transcripts and notes, 08/06/1956-12/16/1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Transcripts and notes, 12/17/1956-03/24/1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Transcripts and notes, 03/1958 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Transcripts and notes, 04/1958 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Transcripts and notes, 07/15/1958-12/28/1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Radio analysis, 01/1959-03/1959 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Radio analysis, 04/1959-06/1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Radio analysis, 07/1959-09/1959 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Radio analysis, 10/1959-12/1959 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Radio analysis, 01/1960-03/1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Radio analysis, 04/1960-06/1960 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Radio analysis, 07/1960-09/1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Radio analysis, 10/1960-12/1960 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Radio analysis, 01/1961-03/1961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- UN reports, 09/1960-12/1961 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Congo transcipts, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Transcripts and notes, 01/05/1962-12/31/1963 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Transcripts and notes, 01/1964-04/1965 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Transcripts and notes, 05/1965-05/1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Transcripts and notes, 05/15/1967-12/31/1968 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Transcripts and notes, 1/1/1969-07/31/1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Transcripts and notes, 08/1/1970-05/26/1971 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Transcripts and notes, 07/04/1971-12/22/1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Transcripts and notes, 01/02/1972-08/27/1973 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Transcripts and notes, 09/05/1973-11/03/1975 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Transcripts and notes, 11/03/1975-08/31/1976 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Transcripts and notes, 09/01/1976-09/30/1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Transcripts and notes, 10/01/1978-04/30/1980 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Transcripts and notes, 05/01/1980-12/30/1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Transcripts and notes, 01/09/1980-12/31/1981 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Transcripts and notes, 01/01/1982-12/31/1983 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Transcripts and notes, 01/17/1984-01/16/1985 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Transcripts and notes, 01/17/1984-10/17/1985 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, press releases, 12/18/1985-04/09/1987 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous: clippings, magazines, correspondence, 1952-1990 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Letter from Richard Hottelet to Robert Cockrum, 1975 May 23 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Recording: America and the World: A First Hand Account of D-Day. Richard C. Hottelet moderator, 1994 June 04 (Box 9, Folder 1, Cassette 1)
  General
  Produced by the Council on Foreign Relations, in association with WNYC/New York Public Radio
- Transcript: America and the World [1/4], 1993-1995 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Transcript: America and the World [2/4], 1993-1995 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Transcript: America and the World [3/4], 1992-1993 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Transcript: America and the World [4/4], 1991-1992 (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Research materials/notes: Afghan, 2002-2003 (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Research materials/notes: Afghan, 1989-1999 (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Research materials/notes, 1980-1987 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Research materials/notes: Mideast, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Research materials/notes: Middle East, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Research materials/notes: United Nations, 1982-1985 (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Research materials/notes: United Nations, Circa 1963-1975 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- Research materials/notes: United Nations, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Research materials/notes: United Nations [1/2[, 1979-2004 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Research materials/notes: United Nations [2/2], 1961-1975 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Research materials/notes: related to United Nations, 1966-1986 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Research materials/notes: US/UN/Allies/Bosnia, 1985-2004 (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Reporter notebook: Germany, 1947 January - March (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Reporter notebook: South America, 1958 June - December (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Reporter notebook: South America and Venezuala, 1959, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Reporter notebooks: I-III, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Reporter notebooks: IV -V, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Reporter notes, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Reporter notebooks: I-III, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 1)
- Reporter notebook: Mideast + Nixon trip, 1969 (Box 13, Folder 2)
- Reporter notebooks: I-III, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Reporter notebooks: IV -VI, 1970 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Reporter notebooks: 1-4, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Reporter notebook: Addis Ababa, 1972 January - February (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Reporter notebook: Panama and Nicaragua, 1973 March (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Reporter notebooks: I - II, 1974 June - October - 1975 (Box 14, Folder 3)
- Reporter notebook:, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Reporter notes, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Reporter notes, 1962-1977 (Box 14, Folder 6)
- Reporter notebook: GA / ME / Wash, 1977-1978 (Box 14, Folder 7)
- Reporter notebook: Deng Xiaoping, 1979 February 03 (Box 14, Folder 8)
- Reporter notebook: Havana Summit, 1979 August 26 - September 09 (Box 14, Folder 9)
- Reporter notebook: Waldheim Trip, 1979 April 22 - May 09 (Box 14, Folder 10)
- Reporter notebooks, 1979 June 11 - 16, 1980 September - October (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Reporter notebooks, 1981 June - December (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Reporter notebook: Middle East, 1981 January - February (Box 15, Folder 3)
- Reporter notebooks, 1982 January - December (Box 15, Folder 4)
- Reporter notebooks, 1982 December - 1983 October (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Reporter notebooks, 1983 October - 1984 October (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Reporter notebooks, 1984 October - 1985 May (Box 15, Folder 7)